>> FEMALE SPEAKER: We are used to think
about sites only with online resources.
But Jake can change our opinion during his
talk on BrazilJS 2016.
Developer for Google Chrome and one of the
editors of the Service Worker specification,
Jake will take an online-only site
and transform it into an offline-first
progressive web app
installable, completely network-resilient,
right before the eyes of the audience.
>> JAKE ARCHIBALD: I landed in Brazil
yesterday and a few people
were asking me were I'm from, and my
standard reply is to say
"I am from England".
And then people say "well, where in England
are you from?" and this used to be
a difficult question to answer, because I'm not
from one of the big cities in England.
I'm not from somewhere many people have
even heard of,
but in the past few years it's actually got
a lot easier to describe to people.
For instance...
[Game of Thrones theme plays]
I moved to the south, in a big city...London!
This is where all the big buildings are...
[Applause]
all the landmarks you're familiar with.
That's the Google office there!
It's where I work, but that's not where I'm
from!
I'm from way up in the north of England in
a small little town called Carlisle.
Now, in Carlisle the buildings are not very
big.
Large parts of the city are in black and white,
it's like there ain't real life, it's really weird.
Not a lot of tech going on, so that's one
of the reasons I had to move out.
But just having the point home, this sort
of purple line here is Hadrian's Wall.
[Laughter] It's really a thing, this thing
was built by the Romans
to keep the wildlings out, or as we call
them, the Scottish.
[Music ends]
[Laughter]
So when I moved down south, I actually
had to sort of change the accent
that I speak with so people could
understand me better.
So instead of saying [Northern England
accent] "Can'ave a pint of beer, please?",
I would say [London accent] "Can I have a
pint of beer, please?".
And instead of saying "I will avenge the death
of Ned Stark!", I'd say...
"I'll have a pint of beer, please".
[Laughter]
So it's a real honor to be opening the conference,
I mean it's great to speak first as well
because it means I don't have to watch a
load of great talks and then worry about
my own not being as good.
I can set a nice low bar right to the start
and enjoy everyone else's talks.
Also, at about 3 p.m. you'll probably find
me just lying face-down on the floor with
jet lag, so don't worry about that, that's
entirely normal.
But this is the first time I've been to South
America and I really want to hear from you
what Chrome and web standards can do better,
because even living in England I can see that
a lot of this stuff can become very
San Francisco-centric,
because that's where a lot of the work happens,
and that's not what I want from the web.
I'm gonna be around for the whole conference,
both days and definitely the after party,
so come and talk to me.
Tell me what the web is not doing right, what
it can do better, even if I'm hiding in the corner,
looking socially awkward, that is because
I am socially awkward, but I'll get over it.
But the thing I wanted to talk about is this.
It's a little web app I built called Emojoy,
well which you can find...
I've got the taskbar itself in there.
Let's get rid of that, there it goes.
You can find it at this URL.
So when you're working developer relations
like I do, you have to build things
from time to time just to prove to yourself and
other people that you're still a real developer,
that you can still actually write code.
And this is what I made.
I turned it into a progressive web app.
And if you're looking to do the same kind
of thing, the first thing we need to do is
to tell the browser how to integrate it with
the rest of the operating system and UI,
in the head of the page you can declare
a theme color,
and this will change the top color,
which is kind of integrated with the browser.
It's a very small thing, but it's a quick
win.
We can also outer-reference to a manifest
and this is downloaded when it's needed.
So the manifest looks like this,
it's just a lump of JSON
that tells it about icons and background colors.
I want to have this, users will be able to
add the site to their home screen
and they get the icon that you specified
along with the title.
But not only that, when they launch it, you get
this splash screen as the browser is booting up
and your site is getting at the first render.
So the background color there, the icon and
the text beneath,
the color right there on the top, that's all
taken from the manifest.
Now once that goes away, the user gets
your site without the URL bar,
so it looks and feels just like a native app.
However, this whole illusion comes crashing
down when you're offline.
I don't know if you've seen, but the offline
screen is actually playable,
it's a little game with the dinosaur.
We had to add an option into Chrome to turn
this game off, because in schools apparently
kids were climbing under the desk and ripping
out the Ethernet cables from the machines,
just so they can play this game.
So we had to add an option to stop that.
But, in general, this is a really bad experience.
The user has launched our app, they've came
to us for content again and we have failed
to such an extent that the browser has to
step in and apologise --
well, they don't apologise, they blame the user.
You see this here, "YOU are offline", it's
your fault.
And this is bad, because if we are competing
with native, this is like an operating system...failure,
it's like when you get that little thing along
the bottom that says
"Abstract Java proxy bin has failed to make
a socket" or something like that,
it's that kind of error.
But things do get worse.
Offline isn't the worst problem we face.
This is.
And I call it Lie-Fi.
[Laughter]
This is when your phone says it has
connectivity, but it doesn't really.
You might experience this sometime today,
because we have Wi-Fi at the conference,
so you'll get something very similar to this.
The Lie-Fi experience...is just this.
So the splash screen goes away when the
website gets to first render,
but when you have Lie-Fi this never happens.
And this is worse than offline, because with
offline you get a quick answer.
The answer is NO, but it's a quick answer.
Here the user is just left waiting,
and you are forcing your users to stare
at this or give up,
and with every passing second the
user hates the experience a little more.
And I don't know if you've been in this situation,
but I'm staring at the white screen
or splash screen and I'm stuck there,
and I think
"well, I'm not going to stop now,
because I feel like if I closed it now,
if I waited one more second that would
have appeared".
It's like "so I'm left in this limbo staring
at the screen".
So this is why we should avoid treating online
and offline as binary states.
If we care for offline and we care for online
separately,
this situation goes completely unsolved.
And that's why the goal standard is offline-first.
Offline-first solves these problems -- I had
so much fun making this slide.
[Laughter]
This is all CSS transforms and mix-blend-mode,
mix-blend-mode is the best thing we've
added in ages!
So, with offline-first we assume offline and
then we do as much as we can with local content,
and THEN we try to go to the network.
And the more we get to render without a
connection,
the more offline-first it is, the better it is.
Because we are thinking of the network as
a piece of progressive enhancements,
and enhancements that might not be there.
And here's how we do.
So to begin with, we register for
a service worker
and this isn't some magic manifest formats
or a config file, it's just JavaScript.
Because you figure it like "why invent some
new thing,
when we have like a world full of JavaScript
developers and debugging tools".
So, after the register call, we should wrap
it into some kind of feature detection because,
you know, there are older browsers out there...
that don't support Service Worker...
[Laughter]
and this just stops them from hurting
themselves... [Laughter]
and others around them.
[Applause]
I should point I'm making fun of IE here,
Edge is implementing Service Worker,
they've got it in their experimental builds,
Edge is a really good browser.
Anyway, in that script I'm gonna add a
listener for the fetch events
and just have a debugger statement in there.
As for now, if I refresh the page, I hit that
breakpoint.
And we got this event object here and it has
a request property, and it's telling me about
the request of the page itself, we can see
the URL, the headers, the type of request.
But you also get one of these events for
every request the page makes,
like the CSS, the JavaScript, the fonts, the
images.
I get these events for the avatar images
even though they are on another domain
or in another origin.
So by default requests go from the page to
the network and there's not a whole lot
you can do about it, but once you
introduce a service worker,
it controls pages and requests go
through it.
But like other events, like "click" and
"submit", you can prevent the default
and do your own thing, and that's where
things get really interesting,
and that's how you can make offline-first work.
So the first thing I built to make Emojoy work
offline is, I created an application shell,
which is just the site without the
messages, just looks like this.
So I want to serve this, and the CSS,
and its JavaScripts
before even thinking about going to
the network.
Because even if we have a great network connection,
serving this from the cache is gonna be
a whole lot faster, and that starts the
offline-first approach.
So we need to cache this ahead of time...
and Service Worker has an event for doing this,
"install",
and this happens the first time the browser
discovers this version of the Service Worker.
And it's your opportunity to go and cache
everything that you need,
so that's what I'm doing here,
I'm creating a cache called "static-v1"
and I'm adding the app shell, the CSS and
the JavaScript too.
But these won't be used by default, the service
worker doesn't really do anything automatically,
you have to tell it what you want.
Overing the fetch events, I'm gonna start
by parsing the URL, so I can look at its
component parts, and then if the request is
to the same origin as the service worker
and the pathname is just "/", I'm gonna
respond with that shell from the cache.
So, event.respondWith() is my way of saying
"hey, I'm gonna take control of this,
I'm going to do my own thing here",
and you're passing a response object
or a Promise that resolves with a response.
And caches.match() takes a request or a URL
and it resolves with a response object.
So that's done.
Oh, also, if we're handling a different path,
I'm going to respond with a match in the
cache for this request,
so if the request is for the CSS or the
JavaScript,
we'll take it straight from the cache.
If it's a different request, then...
caches.match is going to resolve with "undefined".
So we need to catch that and if
response is falsy...
we'll instead fetch the request
from the network.
So here we are treating the cache as a
primary resource for data
and are falling back to the network.
So I'm doing now with whatever connection
the user has.
So it's very offline-first.
So using this pattern we can fetch the app shell,
the JavaScript and the CSS from the cache,
this gives us our first shell render without
going to the network
and now we're running JavaScript on the page,
so I can display even more content gained
from like IndexedDB or LocalStorage or
something like that.
With Emojoy, I show the last set of
messages that was fetched,
the last things the user saw, I just store that
in IndexedDB.
And I don't just do that for offline users,
do it for all users.
And THEN go to the network for updated content.
And update the page when that arrives.
And if that network request fails...
that's kind of okay, I'm still displaying
content, still a good offline experience.
And if that network request is slow, that
is probably okay too, I can tell the user
"hey, we are trying to get data and it's taking
a while", but if the user just came to look
a previous message, then we've given them
that, which is great.
So, to see the benefits of this I wanted to
compare it to the original online-only site,
with this new offline-first service worker
version.
So I went to a place called "The Comparinator".
>> MALE SPEAKER: Fight!
[Laughter]
>> JAKE ARCHIBALD: So, first up, this on the
left here, this is the online-only original
and on the right is the fancy service worker
version.
So this is when the device is online.
Here we see, we get full content instantly.
The one on the left lags behind because it's
having to pull everything from the network.
But in the offline case, we get instant full
content versus a total failure.
But the important case here is the Lie-Fi
one.
Here we get instant full content rather than
the white screen of death.
In fact, with our progressive web app here the
experience is the same with every connection type.
And that's the offline-first goal.
The network only matters when it comes to
fetching new content.
And this is how we compete with native.
And...we can compete with native.
So, I wanted to take this silly little web
app and compare it with a real,
professionally built native app.
So this is Google Photos I'm going to
launch, Google Photos on the left,
and I'm gonna launch Emojoy on the right,
at the same time.
And it's so close!
In terms of performance, it's really competitive.
Emojoy is actually 0.2 seconds slower to
show content, that's 200 miliseconds.
Very close.
And that's comparing to a very well-built
native app.
But this is starting from cold, this is when
the browser isn't in memory at all.
If the user had looked a website recently,
and let's face it, the browser is a pretty
popular app on people's phones, so it's
likely to be in memory, this happens.
You end up with a progressive web app
beating a native app, to content render,
by almost half a second.
A few people have asked me about
Instant Android Apps,
the thing that was mentioned in the I/O,
and my answer was that
"well, progressive web apps are shippable
today", I mean, we saw that in the intro.
These Android Instant Apps, at the
moment it's just the slide deck.
None of this was really sort of seen, what
they can do, how fast they really are,
what screens, the permissions the user has
to agree to see any of this.
Progressive web apps are not Android-only,
it's one thing that you can ship across
thousands of devices, operating systems
and browsers.
And it can beat a native app to content render.
So, Service Worker ship in stable versions
of Chrome, Firefox and Opera.
It's been there for well over an year now.
It's coming to Microsoft Edge, they've just
started landing parts of it in their...
scripted nightly preview browser, it's a
high-priority implementation for them.
It's under consideration by Apple.
They sent some of their senior engineers to
the last Service Worker meeting,
implementation meeting, which was very
encouraging.
But they've not promised if they are going
to ship it yet.
But I'm quietly confident on that.
But progressive enhancement means that you
can use it today.
And if you use Service Worker, your site suddenly
loads faster in Chrome and Firefox and Opera
than they do in Safari, then that gives Apple
more reasons to implement Service Worker,
because they are not in the business of shipping
a slow browser.
Web developers are really in a position of
power here,
and that's the power of the extensible web.
You want to give you low-level things to
play with and to make all your sites faster,
in the way YOU want to make them faster,
rather than providing you with these high-level,
abstract APIs like AppCache that don't
really work for anything.
Anyway, enough about it, this is the stuff
that has been possible for an year now.
I wanna talk a little bit more about stuff
that has just shipped.
Because I've built another app.
This is Wiki Offline.
Because I wanted to show how a service worker
could work for something that was less...
less app-like and more like a traditional
website.
Without Service Worker it's all
server-rendered like Wikipedia itself.
My eventual aim is to make all of the
articles work offline, but in the first pass
I just want it to add a service worker as a
performance enhancement.
As before, I built an app shell.
So, for article pages it would load this
generic shell without the network
and then the page's JavaScript would handle
the fetching of the article from the network.
So, without Service Worker, like any other
website,
but with Service Worker I've re-archictected
it to be more like a single-page app.
So I was very excited about all the work I've
done, I wanted to see how fast it was,
so of course I went back to The Comparinator.
>> MALE SPEAKER: Fight!
>> JAKE ARCHIBALD: I wanted to compare
the original sort of online-only site with the
fancy new service worker version.
So, online-only on the left, service worker
on the right.
And I'm gonna load both of them over
throttled connection,
or as most people in the world call it,
their Internet connection.
So, go!
And I watched this, and I thought:
"Shit".
[Laughter]
It got slower.
It got way slower, here it is again.
So the first render is a bit quicker, but
the content...
which some people would say is the important
part, is over half a second...
oh, it's over two seconds slower on 3G.
And I had about panic about this, because
I was like "oh, we've been working on this
service worker thing for years and it turns
out it's really slow".
But it wasn't Service Worker that was the
problem.
I was using this app shell rather than letting...
I was letting JavaScript do the rest,
like fetch the content and everything.
Which is fine if your design order dictates
that you do this, but it didn't in this case.
I've re-architected the site into a
single-page app.
And single-page apps are incredibly slow,
and this is why I moan about frameworks
all the time.
Here's what it takes a website to get to first
render.
HTML starts downloading...
CSS downloads...
and now start rendering content.
And we continue to render content as more
HTML downloads.
We might download JavaScript too, but,
you know, it should be async,
it's not gonna disrupt the rendering.
If we contrast this to a single-page app,
the HTML downloads...
usually instantly, because it's very small...
CSS downloads...
and then we get our first render.
And that's assuming that the JavaScript
isn't render-blocking, which normally is,
but let's be kind here.
Anyway, this is just a basic UI render.
And then, the JavaScript downloads,
it parses, it executes,
and then it goes about fetching the content
from the network.
And once it has all of the content, it adds
it to the page and we get to render.
And this is how slow happens.
This is why single-page apps can be really slow.
And here in my case I didn't lose much time
on the downloading of the JavaScript
and the downloading of the CSS, because it
was all coming from the service worker,
it was all cached.
The problem is at the bottom here.
The JavaScript has to download ALL of the
content before showing any of it.
The more I think about load time performance,
the more I realize that it isn't about the
size of the CSS, size of the JavaScript, it
all comes down to being progressive.
And this is related to progressive
enhancement, but not quite the same.
I mean, show them what you've got.
All the time you're loading, the user is
watching and waiting.
Don't make them wait until you've loaded
everything before showing them anything.
Prioritise the first render, the first interaction,
show the user what you've got as you get it.
And this is why I was failing, because I was
hoarding content, I was downloading it all
and once I had it all, I was showing it all.
And in retrospect it seems kind of stupid
to be doing this, re-architecting this site
into this single-page app model.
But for me, this was due to AppCache, this
is my AppCache hangover, because AppCache
NEARLY lets you do this page shell pattern,
but not quite, but it lets you get so close that
you can almost smell it, but just at the last
second it stops you with some horrendous bugs.
But once AppCache was out of the way,
I was like "Really? Is AppCache gone now?
Does that mean I can do whatever I want?"
And I just went straight to the thing that
AppCache nearly would let me have,
I went straight back to the page shell model.
What I didn't stop to think is that the best
answer wasn't the one that AppCache
nearly let me have, it was the thing it never
let me anywhere near.
What I wanted was streaming.
So this is a sort of simulation of streaming,
the numbers are reasonably real.
And we can see that with the streaming
model it completes slightly faster than
without streaming, so...streaming
completes, without streaming completes.
The reason for that is the processing is happening
while it's downloading, which is great.
But the biggest win is that some rendering
happens...
ages before the non-streaming version.
It's rendering all the time.
This is the full HTML spec loading here
over throttled connection.
It's a 3 MB document.
It's still downloading, but it gets on screen
after only 20 KB is received.
That's streaming, and this [INAUDIBLE], this
is a benefit for like 10, 20 years.
But for a long time, there's been no access
to streams in JavaScript,
but that is all changing.
Well, we designed the Fetch API alongside
the Service Worker.
We wanted a lower-level representation of
requests and responses, but it was also a
good opportunity to create a much better API
than XMLHttpRequest, because it's a horrible,
you know, that was an old ActiveX thing
that we turned into a web standard.
I think next year XHR turns 18 years old
and I don't want to be using that API
when it's old enough to drink.
It's bad enough as it is.
So when you fetch the URL, you get a
Promise for a response.
We haven't downloaded the whole thing at this
point, this is just when the headers are ready.
And now you choose how to interpret the
response, so things like response.json(),
that returns a Promise, and you'll get your
data at the other side.
And this compresses really nicely with ES6,
arrow functions, and even nicer with
async functions which are being developed
in pretty much all the browsers right now.
So here the keyword "await", it pauses the
execution of the code until the Promise resolves,
but it's paused in an async way, so it
doesn't block the thread.
I think Edge has an experimental version of
this, Chrome Canary I think is about to...
but it produces much easier to read code, so I'm
gonna be using it in the rest of my examples.
If you haven't encountered it before...
it's just you can pretend that async code
is synchronous.
Anyway, you don't have to read the response's
JSON, we provided lots of little helpers
to read as form data, text, blob, array buffers.
And we did this for two reasons.
One, it's a nice convenience feature.
Also, we wanted to ship Fetch before streams
were ready, so we needed to provide another
way of reading the body of the response, for
we reserved response.body() for the stream.
And that's been in Chrome and Opera for
around about a year now,
and it's also being developed by Firefox,
Edge and even Safari.
And here is how to use the stream.
So all I want is to fetch the HTML spec,
but read it as a stream.
First we call getReader(), and this gives
us a lock onto the stream,
so it knows we are the only thing that can
read it, and then we call reader.read(),
and that returns a Promise for some data.
In this result object here, result.done is
true when there's no data left,
otherwise result.value is some data.
In this case, that data is a Uint8Array of bytes.
It's not the whole response, it's just the
first part of it.
If we want the next part, we call
reader.read() again,
and we keep calling that until result.done is true.
So if we wanted to get the length of the
response here, we could do this by
creating a variable for a total and a variable
for the results, create a loop,
and that is gonna read and read and read,
until result.done is true,
and then we can get the value and add its
length to the total, and log that out.
And I'm gonna see if I can get that working
in a live demo.
Well, that needs to be bigger, doesn't it?
There we go.
So, let's see if the Wi-Fi is going to work.
So it's the same code you saw before.
We should see some log in here.
Ah, there it is, this is the HTML spec downloading.
So we can see here that the chunks are all
the same size, I think so it's dictated
partly by the server, partly by the
network stack in the browser.
But what we are actually doing here is inspecting all of these chunks
without having to have the whole response
in memory.
I mean, uncompressed, the whole HTML spec
is about...it's well over 8 MB.
But we are able to look at this without
keeping 8 MB in memory.
The more practical use of this would be to
search the HTML spec for a particular string,
like the word "horse", for example.
So we could do this by reading all of the text
and then seeing "does the text include horse?".
But here we are having to allocate 8 MB of
memory, we're having to download
the whole thing and search across it.
We can do way better with streams.
So instead of fetching all the text, we loop
over the stream, just as we were before.
Now one of the problems we face here is
result.value is an array of bytes,
whereas we want a string to do string matching.
In future this will be really easy, you'll just
be able to pipe
the body through a text decoder, like that.
This would be using a transform stream.
Transform streams haven't been
standardised on the Web yet,
so at the moment you have to do things a
little bit more the long way around.
So I'm gonna getReader(), I'm going to
create a new TextDecoder,
which is a standard that's been around for
a while, and then loop through again.
Here you can see I'm calling decoder.decode
and passing in result.value,
and that will turn the bytes into a string.
This little option there, "stream: true",
that's really important.
I'll show you why it's important.
Let's make that bigger again.
So this is a simple piece of code here, I've
got three Uint8Arrays,
each with three bytes in them.
I'm creating a decoder, and then for each
part I'm going to try decoding it.
And as you can see, the output is garbage.
So, it's not working at all.
But if I add in that "stream: true" option...
oh, that's gonna be a syntax error, there
we go.
Wish I could code.
So happens when you join [INAUDIBLE].
Right, and if I run this...
it works!
Now, what's happening here?
It knows it's a streaming format, so it
knows it's going to...
it's not necessarily getting the whole picture
everytime you call it.
So, we call it with the first three bytes,
and with "stream: true",
it goes "oh, these first three bytes, this is an
incomplete...it's part of an emoji,
but I know it's not complete".
So, it gives back an empty string, but it
holds onto those three bytes.
The next time we call it, we get another three
bytes and it takes that first byte and goes
"oh, if I add this to what I've already got,
I get the poo emoji!
Brilliant, right? I'm gonna hold on to that."
And in the next two bytes, it's like "this
is an incomplete emoji again".
So it gives us the poo emoji back.
Then on the third call we get the final three
bytes and it goes "oh, with those first two,
I can now create the toilet emoji if I add
it to the things I already have",
and then byte 33 there is the exclamation
mark, so returns the string back.
And this is because emoji are four bytes in
UTF-8, which is what we are using here.
Now we can check each chunk of text and see
"does it contain the word horse?".
And if we find a match, we can cancel the
stream and this is great,
because if we find the match in the first,
like, 20 KB,
we can abort the download and save
having to download that whole 8 MB.
But there is a bug in this code.
It's a fairly simple one.
It works fine if our chunks are...
"My lovely", no match.
"horse, running through the field",
there's a match!
Great!
But what if the chunks were...
"My lovely h", no match.
"orse, running through the field", no match.
So we missed the match because neither
chunk contains the word "horse",
the thing we are looking for.
So when you're doing this sort of stuff with
streams, filtering streams, searching streams,
you need to be able to defend against this bug.
To do this we keep a buffer that is the size
of the thing we are searching for, minus 1.
So "horse", five characters, we keep a
buffer of four.
So that means we would see "My lovely h",
no match.
Then when we get the next chunk, we would
add on the last four characters we had,
and we'd match on the word "horse".
The code for that is relatively simple, same
as before, we've got result there.
I'm going to keep a buffer...
loop through the stream, as before, decode
it into the buffer this time
and if we find a match, great, if we don't,
we reduce the buffer down to the last
four characters or whatever the thing we
are searching for is, minus 1.
So now we are searching a large document,
but we are keeping memory usage
really, really low, and we can stop the
download early.
So here is a demo of that on the HTML spec.
Let's see if I can clear this.
This is a bit more of a complicated example,
because I'm making it case-insensitive,
and I'm...keeping more of the results
around, so you can see it.
If I run this again, see HTML spec, once again
searching for "horse"...
there it goes, and there's a match!
There's a match because someone who
contributed to the spec is called Tommy Thorsen,
and he's got "horse" in his name, which is great.
Anyone got other suggestions for words that
might be in the HTML spec, but maybe not?
Poo!
Okay!
You're more polite here, actually.
When I gave this talk in London, there was
silence for a long time,
because no one wanted to say anything,
and then in the back of the room
someone just stood up and pointed out at
me and went: "SHIT"!
[Laughter]
I hope that's a suggestion!
And you're not just commenting.
But I sort of like, quite skeptic, just thought
"oh, it's not gonna be in there, okay",
and I run it and it's like "oh, there's a match!"
What is there a match on?
-- oh yeah, there's canva-"shit"-region!
[Laughter]
It's canvashitregion, but, you know.
I'm curious now, is "poo" in there?
Let's find out.
Oh!
Right on.
Spoofing!
There you go, so "poo" is also in the spec.
Hahaha!
Also, I was talking to some developers in
India, where connectivity is really poor.
When we were doing this, they were sending
a blob of JSON down for some search results.
And a feature they were asking for was like
"Hey, can we detect 3G versus 2G?"
And the reason is they wanted to send
fewer results if it was 2G.
Because they wanted a faster render,
because it's less to download.
But detecting connectivity like that is really
unreliable.
Your phone could be saying you're on 4G,
but you're actually on Lie-Fi.
It's very common in India to be on a 4G
connection, but with 2G speeds.
It's much better to do something like this.
To send something that isn't JSON,
but each line of it is JSON.
Because that becomes a streaming format,
that's really easy to parse
and you can sort of deal with each result as it arrives.
So I got a demo of that as well.
And this is very connection-dependent on whether
this works or not.
So, if I fetch some JSON...
it takes -- okay, so about one, over one second.
It's always faster on the next attempt,
because the connection is there.
So we sort of got 400 miliseconds, but if we
stream it, and sometimes this is no difference...
uh, it's a little bit different.
So we're dealing with it in 300 miliseconds.
But if I...bring up DevTools and throttle
the connection...
let's make that bigger as well.
So in DevTools we've got ways to throttling
the connection here,
so that's what I'm going to do...if I can get
the mouse on that one pixel.
I'm gonna throttle it down to regular 2G,
and let's see how that changes things.
So now if I fetch regular JSON...
this is throttling the connection as well,
it's probably gonna take far too long.
Okay, so it's arriving at about...just on
the five seconds.
With the streaming version, we get the first
bit of data in 300 miliseconds,
and the rest of it is taking the full five seconds.
So if you want a slow connection being up
to stream data like this,
it will allow you to get something on the
screen a whole lot faster.
So you might be wondering how I can use
this speed with my Wikipedia demo.
Well, I can't really, it's completely sad for us.
Because although you can use Fetch to
read a response in little chunks like this,
JavaScript has no access to the streaming
HTML parser.
It might look like here I'm happily adding
HTML into an element, but when you do "+="
like this, you're actually getting and setting,
so it's more like this.
You're asking the browser to take the
article element and turn it into a HTML text,
you serialize all of it, and then you're adding
on more text,
and asking it to parse all of that.
So the elements at the start of the string
get created multiple times and
performance just goes through the floor,
it's a real disaster.
I'm hoping we can provide an API to actually stream HTML into an element,
but it's not there yet.
But in Chrome now, and this is something
we released only a few weeks ago,
you can create your own readable streams.
They look like that, that's the API for it.
You pass it an object with some methods,
like "start", "pull" and "cancel".
So if I wanted to create a stream with
random numbers...
I'm going to create a variable for an interval,
and you'll see why in a moment.
Then I create a stream, and in the "start"
method, which is called straight away,
I'm going to set up an interval that pushes
onto the controller
every second just a random number.
The controller there has other methods like
"close" and "cancel".
Here I'm also going to add a "cancel" method,
so with the person looking at the stream,
once they cancel it, this method will happen
and I'll clear the interval.
Now this is just like a Fetch stream and it
can be read in exactly the same way,
so I'll show you a demo of that.
Here it is, so this is the same code you saw
before, and here I'm going to get reader,
read it three times and then cancel it and
try to read it again.
Uh, if I try to run that code.
Every second we're seeing a number appear,
but then it's cancelled and we don't get a
fourth number.
So this is what we call a push stream,
because we are shoving data into the stream
every second, whether someone is reading
from it or not.
So eventually we're gonna get into memory
problems if no one reads the stream,
because all of these numbers are gonna be
buffered up.
An alternative to this is a pull stream.
So here we create a "pull" method, and this
is only called when the buffer is not full.
So when someone starts reading from it,
when someone has pulled values out of it.
And in here, I can wait a second and
generate a random number.
And I don't need a "cancel" method here because
we're only going to be generating numbers
when someone is asking for them.
So, streams could be of anything as well,
with Fetch we saw them being Uint8Arrays,
here they're numbers, they could be objects,
they could be image elements,
they could be anything.
The designers of streams spent a lot of time talking to the Node folks,
because Node has had like four different
versions of streams and they are very open
about all of the mistakes they've made,
so we were able to fix a lot of them here.
I wanted all of us to make sure that it was
just one stream type, no matter what
the kind of object you're passing through it.
So you might be wondering how I can use
this to speed up my Wikipedia demo.
Well I can't, it's kind of unrelated, not
if using streams on their own, anyway.
But things get a lot more interesting when
we combine with a Service Worker.
So this already streams.
The browser is smart about this, you've passed
in a response object from the network,
it connects the dots and it streams...it
bypasses the Service Worker after headers
and streams to the page.
This also streams, it streams from disk,
from the cache, but in Chrome now,
in the very latest version of Chrome, you can
also create your own streaming responses.
So here I'm going to create a text encoder,
this is the opposite of before,
this is something where I can give it a
string and it turns it into bytes.
Because I'm creating my own Fetch stream,
it has to be a Uint8Array of bytes that we fit
down the wire.
And then I'm gonna create my own stream,
that is going to wait a second,
and then push a paragraph containing a
random number.
And then I'm gonna respond with that.
So new Response, passing a stream,
and I'm gonna set some headers to say
that it's HTML Content Type.
And if I load that...
this is what happens.
We can see the random numbers
appearing, one by one.
But one important detail is that the loader
there is spinning, because as far as the...
the browser is concerned, it is just
receiving an HTML response very slowly.
It's just getting a stream of bytes.
You might be wondering how I can use this
to speed up my Wikipedia demo.
Well, I can!
This is the bit that makes the difference.
Because in that last example we were piping
content straight into the browser's streaming
HTML parser, and that is the key to it all.
This is what AppCache wouldn't let us do.
Instead of turning a perfectly capable
server-rendered site into a single-page app,
I can use Service Worker more like I would
my server.
So what I did for the Wiki Offline is I
fetched the header of the page,
the footer of the page and the body as
three separate requests.
The header and footer are coming from the cache
and the body is coming from the network,
unless the network fails, and then it gets
an error page from the cache.
And then I combine those three streams
together into one stream.
combine() is a function I wrote, it's only
a few lines, but I'm not gonna show it.
Then it creates a single stream that is the header,
and then the body, and then the footer.
And then I can create a new Response
using that combined stream.
And this is like what we do on a server,
we've got text content on a page,
we'll be getting some of it from a template,
some of it from a database,
maybe some of it from a web service,
but we are sending out one response.
And this is the same that we're doing here,
just from my service worker.
Treating your service worker like a server maps
really well to things like blogs and Wikipedia.
And to see the result of this, for one last
time, we go to The Comparinator.
>> MALE SPEAKER: Fight!
>> JAKE ARCHIBALD: Here's how it compares.
So on the left I've got the app shell render
and on the right I've got the streaming
service worker, both over 3G.
And we see the difference in performance
is huge.
We've already seen that the app shell was
slower than just standard network,
so let's compare it to the original server render.
Here they go.
We get the benefit of that cached first
render that is just the bar across the top,
which happens without the network.
And this allows the network stuff to be
happening in parallel,
and it gets on screen quicker because it's
less to fetch,
because it's just the middle body segment.
I'll play it again.
Bang bang, it's on the screen way earlier
than the plain old network version,
even though the content is still coming
from the same network connection.
So, I'm really excited about streams.
That doesn't mean that the app shell model
is bad, it depends on what you're building,
I used the app shell model in Emojoy and it
works really well.
And the result was a PWA that loads faster
than a native app.
A streaming solution would be faster and
easier for you if you use server rendering.
Switching to an app shell model from
server rendering loses you performance,
so avoid that.
If you already use a single-page app,
then you're already suffering
the performance problems of that, so it's fine
to use a page shell in your service worker.
I'd also consider streams if the initial
content may come from the network,
because you'll want to be able to pipe that through.
Also consider streams if a partial content
render is valuable to you.
Which is with Wikipedia, because some of the
Wikipedia articles are really long, but it's
valuable if you can just get the first few paragraphs
down when they have been downloaded.
So this is landing in Chrome, latest version.
It's something that I know.
With Facebook, they're developing a progressive
web app and they're going to use streams,
because they found it to be the fastest solution,
so it's something I really recommend
checking out.
If you wanna know more about it, I've
written an article about them,
because I was really excited about it, and I
do some sillier things here,
like transcoding MPEG to a GIF on the fly,
which I know isn't particularly useful,
but it's something that streams allow you
to do.
And also stuff like this.
Here I'm reading the Wikipedia page for
Cloud Computing.
But using a transform stream to replace every
instance of the word "cloud" with "butt",
which makes it a much easier to read
article, I think.
There's one of my favourite sentences in here,
which is...
that thing is about Oracle, now where is it?
If I could spell.
There it is, yeah!
On 2012, Oracle announced the Oracle Butt.
While aspects of the Oracle Butt are still
in development, this butt offering is p--
I love that phrase, "butt offering"!
[Laughter]
But using a transform stream for this means
I'm not having to download the whole thing
and then do a find and replace and then serve
it, I can do the find and replace on the fly.
So, Service Worker lets us create great user
experiences.
This is Bruce Lawson's logo for the Service
Worker,
because we don't have a better one right now.
I kinda like it, because if you stare at it,
it looks like the colors are changing.
The colors ARE changing, it's got a
CSS filter on there.
Kinda makes me feel drunk, I kinda like it.
I realize I've shown you a lot of code today,
and I got through a lot of it in lightning speed,
but there's a free Udacity course, which I
developed along with some colleagues,
it's fully interactive, where you take an
online-only website to a full offline-first.
It covers the app shell model,
and it covers IndexedDB,
tries to make that a little bit easier
to understand.
Don't worry too much about
remembering the URL,
just Google for "Udacity offline"
and you'll find it.
And with that, thank you very much,
it's been a pleasure.
[Applause]